Hello English learners,
welcome back to
English Pod, my name
is Marko, and I'm Erica.
And today we're bringing
you part two of the
Presidential Farewell speech
of President Eisenhower.
That's right, so we saw in a previous
lesson the beginning of this speech.
Now we're going to look
towards the end of this speech.
Now we must tell you as well that we
did change the speech a little bit, right?
We changed a little
bit to make it a little
bit more comprehensible
and also we did shorten it.
The speech isn't this short.
Okay.
Take out a lot of stuff.
Alright, so again, Marko, why
are we looking at this speech?
What are we learning from it?
Well in this last part of the Presidential
Farewell speech, there are a lot of great
words that are more
difficult and very poetic so
you can use them in
different formal circumstances
or just to sound a little
bit more well-spoken.
Yeah, and we also
again are going to look at
some really quite
difficult and challenging
structures that we hope
you can use maybe when
you're giving a formal
talk or even in your
writing if you want to
sound quite professional.
Okay, very good.
So why don't we listen to the dialogue for
the first time, let's listen how President
Eisenhower says goodbye and then
we'll come back and look at the words.
We now stand ten years
past the midpoint of
a century that has
witnessed four major wars
among great nations, three of
these involved our own country.
Despite the carnage of
these conflicts, America
is today the strongest,
the most influential
and the most productive
nation in the world.
We are understandably
proud of this preeminence,
yet we realize that
America's leadership
and prestige depend not
merely upon our unmatched
material progress, riches
and military strength,
but on how we use our power in the interests
of world peace and human betterment.
Throughout America's
adventure and free
government, such basic
purposes have been to keep
the peace, to foster progress
in human achievement
and to enhance liberty, dignity, and
integrity among peoples and among nations.
We pray that
peoples of all faiths, all
races, all nations, may
have their great human
needs satisfied, that those
now denied opportunity
shall come to enjoy
it to the full, that
all who yearn for
freedom may experience its
spiritual blessings, that
those who have freedom
will understand also
its heavy responsibilities,
that all who are insensitive to the needs
of others will learn charity, that the
scourges of poverty,
disease and ignorance will
be made to disappear
from the earth, and that
in the goodness of
time, all peoples will
come to live together
in a peace guaranteed by
the binding force of
mutual respect and love.
Now, on Friday noon, I am
to become a private citizen.
I am proud to do so.
I look forward to it.
Thank you, and good night.
Well, that certainly was a
very moving speech, hey?
Very moving, and to a certain
point, a little bit religious, huh?
Yeah, I think we'll
talk a little bit about
that a little bit later,
but let's concentrate
on the language now, so
we'll go to language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
All right, on language
takeaway today, we'll
start with our first word,
and it's preeminence.
All right, we are understandably proud
of this preeminence, a preeminence.
So preeminence, what is this?
Basically it's the state of
being the leader of something.
Okay, so in this case, America
was the preeminent nation.
Right, so they were
coming up, they were
very prosperous, so they had
a preeminence in the world.
All right, so I think we can see here, you
can use this as an adjective, a preeminent
nation, or as a noun, an uncountable
noun, the preeminence of our state.
Very good.
We can use this word as
a noun and an adjective.
Why don't we listen to some more examples,
so we can get a better understanding of it.
Example one.
Now, please welcome
Dr. Frank Hicks, the world's
most preeminent
expert on nuclear biology.
Example two.
He's been a leader in
his field for 25 years,
and his preeminence has
never been questioned.
Example three.
Carol Dixon is one of the most
preeminent experts in green technology.
All right, well, Eisenhower
was talking about
all of the things that
the American people
had done since they
became a free nation, and
one of these things was to foster
progress in human achievement.
Foster progress in human achievement.
Well, I like this verb a
lot, to foster something.
So if I say to foster progress or to
foster something, what am I saying?
To help something grow and develop.
To take care of it, to nurse it.
Yeah.
We very commonly hear this
word associated with children, right?
A foster child.
Yeah.
So what's that?
If you have a foster
child, you are basically
taking care of a child because
the parents can't look after them.
It's not like a doppney because you
don't actually, it's not actually legal.
It's just that you're helping
somebody out by raising this child.
Right.
So we can see the
connection there, a foster
child to foster something, but
you know, this is really a great word.
I think it would help to, to give a
couple of examples of how we could use it.
So for example, I can say
our company is looking
to foster better
creativity in the workplace.
Or we could say, here at Praxis language,
we foster the development of your English.
Very good.
So the word foster.
Now moving on in his
speech, he was talking
about nations and faiths
and different types of groups.
And he said, "All who
yearn for freedom.
" All right.
This is a great phrase,
"All who yearn for freedom.
" To yearn.
So to yearn for something.
Now if I yearn for
freedom or I yearn for
something, it's basically that
I really wanted in my heart.
Yeah.
You really wish for it in a
way that's almost painful.
You know, you, you want it so badly.
Now, you wouldn't say like, I'm
yearning for ice cream, would you?
No.
Unless you were locked up in prison
and hadn't had ice cream for 55 years.
Exactly.
So it's usually related to something that's
very difficult to get or something like
freedom or yearning
for, that's really important.
Exactly.
Something very important.
And now for our last word, President
Eisenhower was talking about charity.
He was talking about freedom and
he mentioned the scorges of poverty.
Okay.
So scorges.
The scorges of poverty.
Scorges is a really difficult
but interesting word.
So why don't we hear a few more
examples to help us understand it?
Example one.
Well, there is a disease that continues to
be discouraged to the developing world.
Example two.
One day we hope to
eliminate the scorges of cancer.
Example three.
NATO promises to wipe
out the scorch of terrorism.
So as we can see, the
scorges of something
basically is the cause
of pain or suffering.
So now relating it back to the
text, we see the scorges of poverty.
Yeah, scorges of poverty, scorges
of disease and scorches of ignorance.
All right, so we can see
that poverty, ignorance
and disease cause a lot of
really terrible things, right?
Exactly.
So that's why we say they are scorges.
Okay.
So scorges.
Now, that brings us to the end
of our words for takeaway today.
But you know, as we
talked to earlier, we've
got some really
difficult and interesting
structures to look at
now, influence the builder.
Fluency builder.
Okay.
So, influence the
builder will start off with
the very first sentence
of the paragraph.
We said, we now stand at 10
years past the midpoint of a century.
Okay, so I love this phrase.
We now stand 10 years past
the midpoint of the century.
Now it's interesting because he is making
reference to the future in the present.
And he's using a great phrase to do that.
We now stand.
Now, we can change it a
little bit and use the first part.
We now stand in different circumstances.
So why don't we listen to a
couple of examples example one.
We now stand before you to declare our
love and be united in marriage example two.
I stand before this court and declare
my innocence example three together.
We now stand before
this great challenge and
we will fight arm and
arm to defeat poverty.
All right.
So you can see that
this is a wonderful
phrase to use maybe
in a formal speech, right?
Right.
Or a wedding again or a formal ceremony.
Yeah.
So, and it gives you
this idea, this sort of
very poetic image of
people sort of almost
standing at the cliff,
standing before the, you
know, some big change
that's about to take place.
Exactly.
Ten years past the
midpoint of a century, the
United States has witnessed
four major wars, right?
Okay.
And while he said, despite
the carnage of these
conflicts, America is
today the strongest,
the most influential and most
productive nation in the world.
Okay.
So a great, great, great structure here.
Despite the carnage of
these conflicts, America
today is the strongest
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Right.
Now, let's look at that first word,
despite the carnage of these conflicts.
Okay, so carnage with
that carnage is like a
massacre, right, where
many people got hurt or killed.
Okay.
So a pretty violent situation
when a lot of people died.
And now why does he use this word despite?
Okay.
So he's basically saying, even though we
had all of this death and violence in this
century were still the greatest
nation, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Exactly.
That's exactly it.
I can say, for example, despite the economic
crisis the world is going through our
company has an enormous opportunity
to grow and be more profitable.
Okay.
Or if we want to take
it and imagine we're at
a wedding, we might
say something like this.
We could say, despite
the many difficulties
this couple has faced, they have a
very bright and happy future together.
Very good.
And now if we take
a look at the last
paragraph, it's very interesting
because it's one sentence.
It's a really long sentence.
It's a very long sentence.
So even though it's
not of phrase, let's take
a look at the punctuation
of this paragraph.
Okay.
So Eisenhower starts
out by saying, we pray
that peoples of all
face all races, all nations
may have their great
human needs satisfied.
And then we have a semi-colon there, right?
Right.
So why do we have a semi-colon?
Well, here's what he's doing.
He's saying, we pray for something.
And then he's listing the many
different things that he's praying for.
Okay.
So it's basically a list.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we know that when
you're writing a list,
we commonly use commas
between all the things
that are in this list.
But here, because they
are long and complex ideas,
a comma is not enough,
you need a semi-colon.
Okay.
So we can see here
from the text that the
semi-colon is a great way to separate
ideas, big ideas, complex ideas in a list.
Exactly.
So you can use it and
not necessarily have to end
your sentence or that each
idea become one sense.
You can all just make
it in one big sentence.
Yep.
And actually, I remember back to high school
Marco, my teacher told me, hey, if you
throw in a few semi-colons
into your writing
and do it properly, you'll
really impress people.
All right.
So this is good advice
that you can take and
throw in a couple
of semi-colons, a little
bit of commas here and there and it'll
look like you really know how to write.
Yep.
Okay.
So with that in mind, why don't we listen
to what Eisenhower wrote one last time?
We now stand ten years
past the midpoint of
a century that has
witnessed four major wars
among great nations, three of
these involved our own country.
Despite the carnage of
these conflicts, America
is today the strongest,
the most influential
and the most productive
nation in the world.
We are understandably
proud of this preeminence,
yet we realize that
America's leadership
and prestige depend
not merely upon our
unmatched material
progress, riches, and military
strength, but on how
we use our power in the
interests of world peace
and human betterment.
Throughout America's
adventure and free
government, such basic
purposes have been to keep
the peace, to foster
progress in human
achievement and to
enhance liberty, dignity,
and integrity among
peoples and among nations.
We pray that
peoples of all faiths, all
races, all nations, may
have their great human
needs satisfied, that
those now denied
opportunity shall come
to enjoy it to the full,
that all who yearn for
freedom may experience
its spiritual blessings, that those who
have freedom will understand also its heavy
responsibilities, that
all who are insensitive
to the needs of others
will learn charity, that
the scourges of poverty,
disease, and ignorance
will be made to
disappear from the earth,
and that in the goodness
of time, all peoples
will come to live together
in a peace guaranteed
by the binding force of
mutual respect and love.
Now, on Friday noon, I am
to become a private citizen.
I am proud to do so.
I look forward to it.
Thank you, and good night.
Alright, we're back,
and we're here again
with Pete, our voice
actor for the second part
of the dialogue, and we have a
couple more questions for you today.
Cool.
So, I hear in Eisenhower's speech
that he keeps referencing God.
Like he keeps saying,
"I pray, blah, blah,
blah, blah, he said Godspeed,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
"
So, what's up with that?
Why is he talking about God?
Well, this is a very interesting question.
Traditionally, America
has had a really clear
boundary between
church and state, and you'll
hear a lot of rhetoric
these days that says,
"We're a Christian nation, and we
were founded as a Christian nation.
" Well, that's baloney.
Baloney is not true.
At the time when the
country was founded 200
years ago, it was
overwhelmingly Christian.
If the founding fathers, as we call them,
like George Washington, if they had wanted
a Christian nation,
they could have had it,
they explicitly did not, and a lot of
people since then have gotten that confused.
And now, when we
have a very large Muslim
population, we have
Buddhists, we have people
in all various different
kinds of Mormonism
and everything, it's
even less possible now.
So, I'm kind of baffled when I hear people
say that America is a Christian nation.
But you even have it now in the
coins, like, or on the money, right?
It says in God, we trust.
Right, that started in
the early 20th century.
I think that was Teddy Roosevelt era.
He opposed that.
Roosevelt was really opposed to
that, but-- And then what happened?
They approved it.
Yeah, and, you know,
people said later, like
Eisenhower talking
about this stuff, you know,
in America, we have
something called the Pledge
of Allegiance, which I don't
think you guys probably have.
Not in Canadian.
Obviously, you wouldn't
do it to America, but to your
own, it's kind of like a
salute to the flag, right?
Yeah, it's a little bit nationalist.
I did it growing up,
you put your hand over
your heart and you
face the flag and you say,
I pledge allegiance to
the flag of the United
States of America and to the Republic
for which it stands, one nation under God,
indivisible with liberty
and justice for all.
That part about one nation under God, that
was added in the '50s as a kind of a way of
showing that America is not, quote
unquote, "a godless communist country.
" Wow.
Yeah, because communism teaches, you know,
no religion, and so they-- Wait a minute.
Make sure we're not communist, you know.
Okay, but we don't think that, right?
Yeah, I mean, I'm all about tolerance,
so I think that's kind of absurd.
Okay, so what I think
is really interesting,
though, is that every
political speech, every
time a political leader
has to say something
publicly, he'll always
quote God, right?
Right.
And they'll often end a
speech with, you know,
thank you and God bless
America or something.
Yeah, exactly.
Which, you know what,
for me, as a Canadian is
really strange, like, if
a Canadian president
said God bless Canada, everyone
would-- no one would know what to do.
Yeah.
I don't know, anyway.
I had an ex-girlfriend
who was British and she,
like, Tony Blair started
with that a couple of times.
He said, you know,
and God bless us all or
something, and she
was just put off by it, and
she was like, "The Brits will
never take this," and they didn't.
All right.
The one was impressed.
All right, well, an
interesting feature of
American history, politics, and
society, so thanks to that insight, Pete.
Cool.
My pleasure.
Any comments or any suggestions
about this lesson or any upcoming lessons?
Just let us know.
Or American politics in general.
Well, I'll try to stop in on the forum
and see if I can answer a question or two.
That would be awesome.
So visit us at EnglishPod.com
and Marko, myself,
and Pete are around to
answer your questions.
All right.
We'll see you guys there.
Thanks for downloading and goodbye.